Guide to the Thomas Torrance Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Thomas Torrance Papers
1883-2016
RG 16
Yale University Divinity School Library
3
(7 boxes)
These papers document the work of the China Inland Mission and American Bible Society in Szechuan, West China. Also of significance in the collection are primary source accounts of Chinese Christians, and materials related to Torrance's research among the Ch'iang people in the upper Min valley, including relating to Torrance's theory that the Ch'iang people were of Jewish descent. Thomas Torrance was a missionary in Szechuan, China from 1896 to 1934, first with the China Inland Mission and then with the American Bible Society.
Torrance, T. (Thomas)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Thomas F. Torrance and M. Elizabeth Newlands
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers
Biographical / Historical
1871 Born in Shotts, Lanarkshire, Scotland
1892-1894 Attended Hulme Cliff College in Derbyshire
1894-1895 Studied at Livingstone College, London
1896 Jan Rev. Thomas Torrance arrived in Shanghai.
1896-1910 Stationed in Western Szechuan, working as a missionary with the China Inland Mission, with headquarters in Chengdu.
1909 Serious disagreement with members of the China Inland Mission. Finally settled after ten years.
1910 Withdrew from China Inland Mission due to disagreement. Returned to Scotland. Later persuaded by Dr. John Hykes, Head of the American Bible Society in Shanghai, to return to China to take over the agency of the ABS in Szechuan, centered in Chengdu.
1911 Married Annie Elizabeth Sharp, a missionary with the China Inland Mission, stationed in Kuanshien.
1912-1924 Births of Torrance children: Mary, Thomas F., Grace, Margaret, James, David.
1927 Torrance family left China due to the early communist troubles under Chiang Kai-shek and returned to Scotland. Later, returned to China to continue missionary work, leaving wife and children in Scotland. Remained for seven years.
1934 Returned to Scotland due to Civil War in China. During the revolution, the Ch'iang villages and Christian churches established by Torrance in the upper Min valley were destroyed. Later, Torrance received a New Testament which had been buried to preserve it from the Communists as a symbol of the reestablishment of the Christian Church among the Ch'iang.
1959 Died in Edinburgh
Scope and Contents
These papers provide valuable documentation of mission work of the China Inland Mission and American Bible Society in Szechuan, West China. Also of significance in the collection are primary source accounts of Chinese Christians, and materials related to Torrance's research among the Ch'iang people in the upper Min valley, including relating to Torrance's theory that the Ch'iang people were of Jewish descent.
The Correspondence of Series I is divided into Family Correspondence and General Correspondence. The correspondence between Torrance and his family dates from the period when he was in West China and the family was in Scotland, for the children's education, 1928-1934. This was a turbulent period in the history of West China, due to the emergence of the Communist party. Torrance returned to Scotland in 1934 and there heard of Mao Zedong's destruction of Ch'iang Christian churches.
The General Correspondence dates from 1906 to 1955 and deals primarily with Torrance's relations with the China Inland Mission and American Bible Society. A section of letters relating to the Vale/Torrance case and Torrance's departure from the China Inland Mission was restricted until 1999 but it now open.
The Writings of Series II include material written by Torrance, the memoirs of his wife, Annie Elizabeth Sharp Torrance, and material collected by Torrance. Torrance's writings include an unpublished manuscript of conversion stories of Chinese Christians, miscellaneous other stories of Chinese Christians, published articles and leaflets, and reports of his work.
Annie Torrance's memoirs date from 1883 to 1927; they document her work as a missionary serving under the China Inland Mission and the period following her marriage to Torrance. The writings collected by Torrance include reviews of his writings, Chinese manuscripts, and numerous articles related to West China and the Ch'iang people.
The Personal Items and Memorabilia of Series III include Chinese travel passes and a Chinese scroll tribute to Torrance.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1909-1935
II. Writings, 1883-1984
III. Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1897-2013
Missions -- China; Missionaries; Torrance, T. (Thomas)
- Correspondence, 1909-1987; Series I
  - Family Correspondence
    - From future wife, Annie Elizabeth Sharp (called Betty) To wife, Betty, 1909, 1912 May 12 (Box 1, Folder 1a)
    - To wife, Betty, 1912 May 12 (Box 1, Folder 1b)
    - To wife, Betty, 1928 Mar-Aug (Box 1, Folder 1c)
    - To wife, Betty, 1928 Sep-Dec (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - To wife, Betty, 1929 Jan-May (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - To wife, Betty, 1929 Jun-Dec (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - To wife, Betty, 1930 Jan-May (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - To wife, Betty, 1930 Jun-Oct (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - To wife, Betty, 1931 Jan-May (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - To wife, Betty, 1931 Jun-Dec (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - To wife, Betty, 1932 Jan-Jun (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - To wife, Betty, 1932 Jul-Dec (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - To wife, Betty, 1933 Jan-Jun (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - To wife, Betty, 1933 Jul-Dec (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - To wife, Betty, 1934 Jan-Jun (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - To wife, Betty, 1934 Jul -1935 Jan (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - To niece, Annie Thomson, 1911, 1913, 1922 (Box 2, Folder 14a)
    - To children (Mary, Thomas F., Grace, Margaret, James, and David), 1928 Jan-Mar (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - To children, 1928 Jul-Dec (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - To children, 1929 Jan-Jun (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - To children, 1929 Jul-Dec (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - To children, 1930 Jan-Jun (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - To children, 1930 Jul-Dec (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - To children, 1931 Jan-Jun (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - To children, 1931 Jul-Dec (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - To children, 1932 Jan-Jun (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - To children, 1932 Jul-Dec (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - To children, 1933 Jan-Sep (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - To children, 1934 Jan-Jun (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - To children, including one letter from Annie Elizabeth Torrance to Mary; undated letter from Mary (ca. 1917), 1934 Aug-1935, 1952-1957, no date (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - General Correspondence
    - American Bible Society (primarily to John R. Hykes, Agent), 1911 Aug-Dec (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - American Bible Society (primarily to John R. Hykes, Agent), 1912 Jan-Apr (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - American Bible Society (primarily to John R. Hykes, Agent), 1912 May-Oct (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - American Bible Society: CD of scans of Thomas Torrance papers held by American Bible Society (64 documents), 1911-1929 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - British Museum, Department of Ceramics and Ethnography (R. L. Hobson), 1931 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Cameron, Mr., 1928-1932 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Ethnographic Museum, Munich, 1914 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Hykes, John R. (American Bible Society), 1917-1920 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Lacy, Carleton, 1923-1931 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - To "Friends", 1906-1931 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Koo, D. Z. (secretary to Madame and Gen. Chiang Kai-shek), 1937 Jun (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Plewman, T.E., 1935 (Box 3, Folder 35a)
    - Ramsey, Clarence H. C., 1935 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Reynolds, Johanna Madson, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Vale/Torrance Case: China Inland Mission and American Bible Society, 1909-1923 (Box 7, Folder 95-116)
  - Of Thomas F. Torrance (son)
    - With Archie Crouch re. Crouch's correspondence with David A. Leventhal; includes photo of Nestorian monument, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 83a)
- Writings, 1883-1984; Series II
  - Thomas Torrance
    - Newspaper articles, bibliography
      - Published newspaper articles, including "Rock Cut Tombs of Szechuan", "The Man-Tsi Caves of Western Szechuan", 1908-1923, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 38)
      - Bibliography of Published Works (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Unpublished writings
      - Book (unpublished): Conversions Stories of Chinese Christians (Box 4, Folder 40)
      - Drafts of book chapters:: Chapter 1: The Story of Tang Kuang-Ching (Box 4, Folder 41)
      - Chapter 2: The Story of Ko Ta-Niang (Box 4, Folder 42)
      - Chapter 3: The Story of Han Shen-Chih (Box 4, Folder 43)
      - Chapter 4: Eventide Conversions (Box 4, Folder 44)
      - Chapter 5: The Story of Teacher Ho (Box 4, Folder 45)
      - Chapter 6: The Story of Pan Ting-Shan (Box 4, Folder 46)
      - Chapter 7: The Story of Mrs. Pan Been- (Box 4, Folder 47)
      - Chapter 8: The Story of Hsu Wan-Liang (Box 4, Folder 48)
      - Chapter 9: The Lord's Day Experiences (Box 4, Folder 49)
      - Chapter 10: The Story of Chen Yuen-Chang (Box 4, Folder 50)
      - Chapter 11: The Story of Yuin Bow-Chen (Box 4, Folder 51)
      - Chapter 12: The Story of Liu Han-Chang (Box 4, Folder 52)
      - Chapter 13: The Story of Jacob Jang (Box 4, Folder 53)
      - Chapter 14: Cases of Sudden Conversion (Box 4, Folder 54)
      - Chapter 15: The Story of Daniel Deow (Box 4, Folder 55)
      - Chapter 16: The Story of Ho Kin-Shan (Box 4, Folder 56)
      - Chapter 17: The Story of Chen Fu-Kuan (Box 4, Folder 57)
      - Chapter 18: The Story of Ong Gwang-Ming (Box 4, Folder 58)
      - Chapter 19: The Story of Ren Jen-Bang (Box 4, Folder 59)
      - Chapter 20: The Story of Chen Bing- (Box 4, Folder 60)
      - Chapter 21: The Story of Isaac (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - Miscellaneous stories
      - "Free Translation of a letter from Colporteur Hou Li-Teh who was caught and impressed as a soldier" (Box 5, Folder 62)
      - "The Question of Baptism", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 62)
      - "The Story of Gow Sho-Be and His Family" (Box 5, Folder 63)
      - "The Story of Hsiung K'in An", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 63)
      - "The Story of Rev. Jo Pei-Lin", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 63)
      - "The Story of Liu Been-Hsuin", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 64)
      - "The Story of Yo Bay-Yin", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 64)
      - Story fragments, poems, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 64)
    - Published articles, books, and leaflets
      - "The Basic Spiritual Conceptions of the Religion of the Ch'iang", 1934 (Box 5, Folder 65)
      - "The Bible in China", 1939 (Box 5, Folder 65)
      - "Burial Customs in Szechuan", 1910 (Box 5, Folder 65)
      - "Chang Hsien Chong: The Spoiler of Szechuan", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 66)
      - "China's First Missionaries"; incl. essay about this book written by Thomas F. Torrance, 1937, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 66)
      - "The Chinese Cat", 1926 (Box 5, Folder 66)
      - "The Early History of Chengtu", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 67)
      - "The Emigrations of the Jews: Israel in China", 1940 (Box 5, Folder 67)
      - "The Eternal Ten Commandment" (Box 5, Folder 67)
      - "Evangelism in West China", 1930 (Box 5, Folder 67)
      - "The Forgiveness of Sin", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 67)
      - "Free Translation of a Stone Tablet at Lifan", 1933-1934 (Box 5, Folder 67)
      - The History, Customs and Religion of the Chiang, 1920 (Box 5, Folder 68)
      - "The History of the Shuh: A Free Translation of the Shuh Chi", 1924 (Box 5, Folder 69)
      - "My Work Among the Tribes", 1935 (Box 5, Folder 69)
      - "Notes on the Cave Tombs and Ancient Burial Mounds of Western Szechwan", 1930-1931 (Box 5, Folder 69)
      - "Notes on Monotheistic Beliefs in the Far East", 1952 (Box 5, Folder 69)
      - "Notes on the West China Aboriginal Tribes", 1932 (Box 5, Folder 69)
      - "On an Evangelizing Tour Among the N. W. Tribes", n.d. (Box 5, Folder 70)
      - "The Origin and History of the Irrigation Work of the Chengtu Plain", 1924 (Box 5, Folder 70)
      - "The Peach Garden Pact" (by TTT?), n.d. (Box 5, Folder 70)
      - "The Religion of the Ch'iang", 1923 (Box 5, Folder 70)
      - "Religious Life in China from Ancient to Modern Times", 1928 (Box 5, Folder 70)
      - "The Survival of Old Testament Religious Customs Among the Ch'iang People of West China", 1939 (Box 5, Folder 71)
      - "The T'ieh-Ch'i Earthquake of August 1933 and Afterwards" (Box 5, Folder 71)
      - "The Use of Stones in Primitive Worship", 1936 (Box 5, Folder 71)
      - "Work Among the Ch'iang Tribesmen", 1930 (Box 5, Folder 71)
    - Reports of work
      - Chengtu, West China, 1915-1933, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 72)
      - Songpan, Szechuan, 1932 (Box 5, Folder 73)
      - Szechuan, 1933-1934 (Box 5, Folder 73)
      - Unidentified, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 74)
      - Hospital Work, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Related Writings Collected by Torrance
    - Book reviews of Torrance's writings
      - Reviews of China's First Missionaries by: Dye, Daniel S and unidentified, 1937, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 76)
    - Chinese manuscripts
      - Ch'iang Sacrificial Rites by Joseph T. (copy of small book), 1925 (Box 5, Folder 77)
      - Old Testament is Just the Same as the Practice of Our Tribe", including English translation, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 78)
      - Prayer by Anbang Yang, 1922 (Box 5, Folder 79)
    - Chinese tracts
      - Including "World's Foremost Question" and tract by Ch'iang-min convert, pre 1935 (Box 6, Folder 80)
  - Annie Elizabeth Sharp Torrance
    - Memoirs, 1883-1927 (Box 6, Folder 81)
  - Thomas F. Torrance (son)
    - "The Visit of Thomas F. Torrance to Chengdu, the capital of Sichuan, and to Weichow and Chiang Villages in Wenchuan County, the upper Min Valley, Sichuan, 1986 Oct 4-18" (Box 6, Folder 82)
    - "Journal of my Visit to Hong Kong, Chengdu and Wenchuan, April 22 - June 3, 1994" (Box 6, Folder 83)
  - Writings of others
    - Wong How-Man, "Peoples of China's Far Provinces, National Geographic, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 84)
    - Plewman, T. E., "The Red Terror in the Tribes Country", "Report of a Journey to Weikiu, Lifan and Tzagulas", 1935 (Box 6, Folder 84a)
    - "China and the Old Testament", N.C. Daily News, Shanghai, 1923 Jan 19 (Box 6, Folder 85)
    - Re. Discussions about Isaiah 49:12 concerning "Sinim", meaning China or Syene, Egypt, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 86)
    - McGovern, William M., Pages from The Early Empires of Central Asia, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 87)
    - Lowenthal, Rudolf, "The Jews in China: a Bibliography", The Yenching Journal of Social Studies, Vol 1,No.2, Peking, China, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 88)
    - Bergen, P.D., "The Sages of Shantung:Confucius and Mencius", 1913 (Box 6, Folder 89)
    - Cheng Te-K'un, "Szechwan Pottery", from Apollo Annual, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 89)
    - Edgar, J.H., High Altitudes: Missionary Problems in Kham or Eastern Tibet, Chengtu, Szechwan, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 89)
    - Ferguson, Peter Blair, Index to the Journal of the North China Branch of the Royal Asiatic Society Vo. I to Vol. LIV (supplement), 1924 (Box 6, Folder 89)
    - Graham, David Crockett, "The Ancient Caves of Szechwan Province, China", Proceedings of the United States National Museum, vol. 80, Art. 16, pp. 1-13, plates 1-16, 1932 (Box 6, Folder 89)
    - Hartwell, Dr. (Grandpa Ho), A Rhyming Journey from Chengtu, Szechuan to "Merry Old", England (Box 6, Folder 90)
    - Hykes, John R., List of Translations of the Scriptures into the Chinese Language, 1915 (Box 6, Folder 90)
    - Lacy, Carleton, "A Century of Bible Work in China", The Chinese Recorder, 1934 (Box 6, Folder 90)
    - Lessing, F., Ostasiatische Plastiken, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 90)
    - Liljestrand, S.H., "A Resume of BorderResearch and Researchers", Journal of the West China Border Research Society, 1934 (Box 6, Folder 91)
    - Pollak, Michael, Mandarins, Jews, and Missionaries: The Jewish Experience in the Chinese Empire, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 91)
    - Robin, Dr. "Let's Drop Education and Just Preach the Gospel", Reprint from S.P.G. Mission Field, Shantung Christian University, Tsinan, China (Box 6, Folder 91)
    - Rock, Joseph F., "The Land of the Tebbus", Reprint from The Geographical Journal, Vol. 81, No. 2, 1933 Feb (Box 6, Folder 91)
    - Seligman, C.G., "The Roman Orient and the Far East", Reprint from Antiquity, 1937 Mar (Box 6, Folder 91)
    - Vale, Joshua, "Irrigation of the Ch'eng-tu Plain", Journal of the China Branch of the Royal Asiatic Society, Vol. 33, 1902 (Box 6, Folder 91)
    - Border Mission Bulletin (in Chinese, with English translations of some articles), 1945-1947 (Box 6, Folder 92)
    - "The Late Dr. J.H. McCartney of Chungking" (author unidentified), n.d. (Box 6, Folder 93)
    - List of Directors, Members of Councils,Missionaries and Stations of the China Inland Mission, Shanghai, 1937 (Box 6, Folder 93)
    - The West China Missionary News, Vol. 28, No. 7-8, 1926 (Box 6, Folder 93)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1916-2016; Series III
  - Wills of Thomas Torrance and Annie Elizabeth Torrance; Statement of Investment Certificate; calling cards, marriage and memorial cards for relatives, article found in TTT's Bible; two cross-stitched mementos, 1897-1934, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 94)
  - Obituary of TTT; biographical statement re. Torrance written by his son, Thomas F. Torrance; letter from M Elizabeth Newlands (granddaughter) that includes biographical information, 1959, 1996, 2013 (Box 6, Folder 94)
  - Four travel passes in Chinese, 1916-1935 (Box OV-d)
  - Chinese scroll - tribute to Thomas Torrance, 1927 December 25 (Box OVd-5)
    Scope and Contents
    Tributes written by 12 of his friends/colleagues in China. A copy has been engraved on stone at the church he established.
  - Replica drawing of Map of Sites of Missionary Work in Aba Region (陶然士手绘阿坝州传教所到处地图)., no date (Box OVd-5)
    The original work, drawn by Mr. Thomas Torrance, is kept by Mr. Xichun Wang, a resident of Wenchuan District, Aba Region, Sichuan Province, China.
  - Booklet of photographs from Sichuan University Museum Special Exhibition: The Rev. Thomas Torrance (1871-1959), International Museum Day, May 18, 2016. Taken by Torrance's granddaughter Grace Torrance Lennox. (Box 6, Folder 95)